Guide to the S. J. Sedgwick Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
S. J. Sedgwick collection
1868-1895
WA MSS S-2360
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.13
3 boxes + 2 broadside + 1 portfolio
The S. J. Sedgwick Collection consists of manuscript notes and drafts for several of S. J. Sedgwick's slide lectures on the West ("Big Trees and Yosemite Valley," "Central Pacific Railroad," "Indians," and "Monterey, California") and one on geology; the manuscript draft and later proofs of the 4th edition of "Announcement of Professor S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery of ... the Rocky and Sierra Mountains...", produced by the Union Pacific Railroad Company; and a scrapbook documenting his work for George A. Crofutt, publisher of a series of western travel guides. There are also printed bills and advertisements for Sedgwick's lectures. Both woodcuts and printed maps are included in the collection.
Sedgwick, S. J. (Stephen James)
Crofutt, George A.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired by gift and purchase from various sources as indicated on individual folders. Source information is recorded in the finding aid or on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1871-1895. II. Scrapbook, 1869-1886. III. Lectures, 1870-1890, undated. IV. Advertisements, 1868-1882, undated. V. Lantern Slide Catalogs, 1876, undated. VI. Other Papers, undated.
S. J. Sedgwick
S. J. Sedgwick was born near Geneva, New York, circa 1820. He became a principal in the Buffalo public school system at age 22, and went on to establish his own school, the Metropolitan Academy and Gymnasium, in New York City in 1852. He also edited the "Gymnast," a paper dedicated to physical education. In 1857, he received a Master's Degree from Union College, and taught in New York City public schools from 1858 until the Civil War. Following the war, he joined the photographic corps of the Union Pacific Railroad Company. When he returned to New York, he developed a popular series of lantern slide lectures called "Across the Continent," showing the West from Omaha to the Pacific. In 1873, Sedgwick worked as an agent for "Crofutt's Trans-Continental Tourists' Guide," travelling again throughout the West. Sedgwick also lectured on world religions, geology, astronomy, and art history.
Scope and Contents
The S. J. Sedgwick Collection contains manuscript notes and texts for 4 of S. J. Sedgwick's slide lectures on the West ("Big Trees and Yosemite Valley," "Central Pacific Railroad," "Indians," and "Monterey, California") and one on geology, as well as the manuscript draft and later proofs of the 4th edition of "Announcement of Professor S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery of ... the Rocky and Sierra Mountains...", produced by the Union Pacific Railroad Company. There are also 2 photographs of the State of Washington ferry; a scrapbook documenting Sedgwick's work for George A. Crofutt, and a scrapbook documenting his work for George A. Crofutt, publisher of a series of western travel guides, which includes his contract, diary entries, correspondence with Crofutt, clippings, and 2 printed maps; other business correspondence; printed bills and advertisements for the "Across the Continent" series and other lectures, many with woodcut illustrations after photographs; photographers' lists of lantern slides available for sale; and other papers.
Indians of North America; Geology, Stratigraphic -- Silurian; Advertisements; Lecturers; Stereoscopic views -- Catalogs; Union Pacific Railroad Company; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Trade catalogs; Naturalists; Posters; Central Pacific Railroad Company; Monterey (Calif.) -- Description and travel; Yosemite Valley (Calif.) -- Description and travel; Woodcuts (prints); Maps (documents)
- Correspondence, 1871-1895; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains business correspondence pertaining to S. J. Sedgwick's "Across the Continent" lecture series.
  - Business correspondence, on pages once part of a scrapbook, arranged chronologically, 1871-1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook, 1869-1886; Series II
  Series II is arranged alphabetically.
  Series II consists of scrapbooks belonging to S. J. Sedgwick. Included are Sedgwick's contract, diary entries, correspondence with George A. Crofutt, and loose clippings.
  - "Crofutt's Trans-Continental Tourists' Guide," scrapbook documenting work as a Crofutt agent, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Loose clippings received from between pages 35-36 of scrapbook (preservation copies), 1869-1886 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Loose clippings received from between pages 35-36 of scrapbook (originals), 1869-1886 (Box 4 (Portfolio), Folder 28)
- Lectures, 1870-1890, undated; Series III
  Series III is arranged chronologically.
  Series III consists of manuscript notes and texts for 4 of S. J. Sedgwick's slide lectures. Included is a manuscript draft--accompanied by later proofs--of the 4th edition of "Announcement of Professor S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery of ... the Rocky and Sierra Mountains...".
  - "Central Pacific Rail Road," manuscript text for slide lecture, Newtown [New York], 1870 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Indians," manuscript text for slide lecture, Newtown, 1871 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Announcement of Prof. S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in all Parts of the Rocky Mountains, between Omaha and Sacramento, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Announcement of Prof. S. J. Sedgwick's illustrated course of lectures and catalogue of stereoscopic views of scenery in all parts of the Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains, between Omaha and San Francisco, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Announcement of Professor S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in all Parts of the Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains between Omaha and San Francisco, [1879] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of the State of Washington ferry showing the ferry going up and downstream for Announcement of Professor S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in all Parts of the Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains between Omaha and San Francisco, circa 1879 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 21)
  - Announcement of Prof. S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in all Parts of Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains between Omaha and San Francisco, 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Announcement of Prof. S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in all Parts of the Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains between Omaha and San Francisco, 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "No. II. Big Trees & Yosemite Valley," manuscript notes and text for slide lecture, Newtown, 1890 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Monterey, California," manuscript text for slide lecture, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "II. Lecture," manuscript text for geology lecture about the formation of the Earth and Silurian life forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Advertisements, 1868-1882, undated; Series IV
  Series IV is arranged chronologically.
  Series IV consists of printed bills and advertisements for S. J. Sedgwick's "Across the Continent" series and other lectures.
  - Printed advertisements for S. J. Sedgwick's "Across the Continent," religion, and art history lecture series, 1868-1882 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Prof. S. J. Sedgwick, A.M., Respectfully announces [...]," flyer for "Across the Continent," Astoria, 1874 January (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Third Grand Dime Entertainment [...]," flyer for S. J. Sedgwick's lecture series at the Cooper Institute, 2 copies, 1877 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Poster for "Across the Continent" series, 1878 March (Box Broadside, folder 26)
  - Manuscript text advertising S. J. Sedgwick's "Across the Continent" lecture series, Brooklyn, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Printed advertisements or window cards for "Across the Continent," with woodcut illustrations, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 22)
  - Posters for "Across the Continent" series, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 23)
  - Poster for "Across the Continent ," printed in red and blue, with manuscript corrections, undated (Box Broadside, folder 27)
  - Printed advertisements for slide lectures by Charles Harvey and E. O. Beaman (annotated), undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Lantern Slide Catalogs, 1876, undated; Series V
  Series V is arranged chronologically.
  Series V consists of lantern slide catalogs of William I. Marshall and Wm. Notman & Son.
  - William I. Marshall, "Photographs of Wonderland, or Views in the Yellowstone National Park," list, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wm. Notman & Son, Montreal, list of slides of Manitoba, North West and Pacific, annotated, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 24)
- Other Papers, undated; Series VI
  Series VI arranged alphabetically.
  Series VI consists of S. J. Sedgwick's manuscript notes and woodcut illustrations made by J. D. Woodward.
  - Manuscript notes and lists of people, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Woodcut illustrations of scenes in Virginia by J. D. Woodward, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 25)